Lowell Thomas Film Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Lowell Thomas Film Collection
1919-1975
NPKMC-222-111
Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981
3933 Cans of Film 681 Linear Feet
The Lowell Thomas Film Collection encompasses a wide range of materials documenting the travels of Lowell Thomas and Lowell Thomas Jr. These materials include 35mm motion picture prints and negatives, 16mm motion picture film and ¼ inch audio tape.
Marist College Archives and Special Collections 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
There are no restrictions on this collection
It was the declaration of war in 1917 that initiated Lowell Thomas’s travels across the globe. He would document what was happening on the war front and report back to his fellow Americans to aid in the war effort. Though after a short period of time filming the war efforts, Thomas felt his work would be better suited elsewhere and after given the opportunity to capture the British war in Arabia, he gladly accepted. While on this trip he met General Edmund Allenby and T.E. Lawrence. He spent days with Lawrence, photographing and filming him - materials that would later be used in one of Thomas’s travelogues.
Afterwards, Thomas continued his travels to Burma, India, Malaya, Europe and Russia. All the while filming, and documenting each journey. Many of these trips were presented to the public via travelogue productions and books that Thomas wrote. In 1930 Thomas became a radio broadcaster, presenting ‘Lowell Thomas and the News’ for 46 years on NBC and CBS radio.
Later, in 1954, Thomas along with a group of investors purchased majority control of the Hudson Valley Broadcasting Company. In just a few short years the company became known as Capital Cities Communications. With the purchase of a television station in Albany, New York and several radio stations Capital Cities became a national company. During his time with Cap Cities, as it came to be known, Thomas produced a series of travelogues under the name of ‘High Adventures with Lowell Thomas’. Places such as Russia, Nepal, New Guinea and Africa were just some of the areas of focus.
Read more
The Lowell Thomas Film Collection consists of video tapes and motion picture films arranged by form of material into two subseries. The subseries are divided further into sub subseries arranged by form of material or subject. Of particular interest are the motion picture films related to Thomas's Cinerama productions, the "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" series, and the journey to Tibet. Also of interest are the films of interviews and lectures given by Thomas or Lowell Thomas, Jr. A project to digitize these recordings is on-going. Materials without digital versions may be digitized at the researcher's expense. Researchers should consult with the archivist regarding the available digital versions.
Thomas, Lowell, 1923-2016
Collection is arranged into nineteen series: 1) Africa, 2) Alaska, 3) Arctic, 4) Australia, 5) Belgian Congo, 6) Danger Island, 7) India, 8) Intros, 9) Nepal, 10) New Guinea, 11) Russia, 12) Sinbad, 13) Tibet, 14) Venezuela, 15) Atomic, 16) Bertha Vester, 17) Cinerama, 18() East Asia, and 19) Home Movies
The Lowell Thomas Film Collection was donated to Marist College by the Thomas family in 2006 and 2013.
The Marist College Archives and Special Collections staff wishes to express their deep appreciation to all of the parties that helped the Lowell Thomas Project come to fruition. [Read more](https://archives.marist.edu/LTPHistoricalNote/views/acknowledgements.html)
Lowell Thomas Memorabilia Collection
Lowell Thomas Papers: Graphic Material
Lowell Thomas Papers: Objects
Lowell Thomas Papers: Sound Recordings
Lowell Thomas Papers: Textual Materials
- 1. Africa, 1944-1977; 371 cans
  - Africa, 352 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1)
    Preview for "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" Tibet episode with commercial for General Motors Delco-Remy batteries. Also contains brief clips mentioning other episodes of "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas", including the Congo and Timbuktu.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Africa, 416 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 2)
    Lowell Thomas narrates a show on Timbuktu, Mali, focusing on the value of salt in this region.; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Cricket Sequence, 119 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 3)
    On the film audio track you can hear people singing and clapping. You also hear people talking in another language.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - King Coapman Darts on Table, 1949; 135 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 4)
    Two men show the camera what looks like tranquilizer darts.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - King Coapman on elephant, 125 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 5)
    Men speak with each other about how they're going to herd elephants and the separations between the mothers and babies.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - King Coapman darts on Table, 142 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 6)
    Two men speak together about the sedation drugs that they will use on an elephant that is about to give birth. The doctor speaks to the man about what he has to do to help him get the calf out safely.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - King and Coapman on Elephant, 1949; 222 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 7)
    Men on safari are filmed riding elephants.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Camp Act. - Cooking + Ele., Terai - Buff. + Birds, 156 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 8)
    Shots of a village preparing food. One man cooks food over a fire. Another grinds up peppers with a stone. Elephants throw dirt on themselves in the background.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - King Feeding Rhino and Applying Ointment, 1957; 255 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 9)
    The film showed a man petting a rhino and feeding it grass.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Elephants Wash, 51 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 10)
    Sounds of men shouting and water splashing. The men are trying to trap an animal.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Rejects, 107 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 11)
    Audio of Lowell Thomas talking about African safaris.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Discussion Misc Animals Sunsets, 144 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 12)
    The film showed trees and bird flying. It showed Lowell Thomas sitting on an elephant with two other people and it showed a man taking pictures.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - G.O., no title, Monk, smokey mts new found Durrane, GM, F, JJ, GC,G, 211 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 13)
    The film showed people riding on elephants, it showed people carrying things, it showed people washing clothes, it showed a man praying and it showed a large crowd of people.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Hunt Discussion Misc. Animals, Sunsets, 1949; 215 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 575)
    The film showed the sun setting, it showed an river, it showed people riding on elephants, it showed people sailing a boat and it showed trees.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Elephants Training - Outs, 218 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 14)
    The film showed people riding elephants and it showed men firing guns.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Capital Cities, 1949; 318 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 15)
    The film showed men carrying people in basket carriage, it showed people riding on elephants, it showed people carrying things, it showed an elephant eating and it showed people working.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - unlabeled, 1969; 316 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 16)
    Film of a parade. People carrying a man in chairs and playing instruments. People riding elephants on a safari. A baby rhino crosses the road. People selling vegetables at a food market.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - unlabeled, 1969; 312 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 17)
    A man gets carried down a road by his friends. Cut to a man carrying vegetables back to his village. Lowell Thomas rides an elephant through a shallow river.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - N/A, 1949; 322 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 18)
    Men carrying produce to sell at the market. A baby rhino is sighted while Lowell Thomas is riding an elephant on safari. People shopping and gathered together.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Unlabeled, 1949; 323 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 19)
    The filmed showed a man cooking and showed Lowell Thomas standing next to two other men talking. It showed people in trees, showed cars driving by, showed people riding elephants and showed men carrying people in basket carriages. The film showed people walking around and it showed people walking around.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - N.B.C T.V Donald B. Hyatt (3 Rolls) Head Picture Orig. Neg. N6876, 1954; 87 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 20)
    We are shown an African village surrounded by a fortress. The women of the village gather straw into a large pile. The camera focuses on the women's many piercings and body modifications. The men of the village continue to built their huts and fortress. An American military man plays with his dog in the village. Men prepare for a fight and aim their guns and spears over the fort. Shots of snowy mountains.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Elephant Feet Thru Grass & Water, 95 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 21)
    On the audio track you can hear loud noise, people talking in the background and you hear animal noises.; Format: 35mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Elephant Feet Thru Grass & Water, 102 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 22)
    The film showed elephants walking and people riding them.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Screaming mahuts, Dr. Wife takes data, 1949; 106 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 23)
    On the audio track you can loud commotions of people talking in another language. You also hear a man giving numbers for pulse, respiration and temperature; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Screaming mahuts, Dr. Wife takes data, 1949; 57 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 24)
    The film showed people riding on elephants and it showed a woman writing in a book.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, N/A - Audio track only; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - L.S. Party Into Stream Coapman Alone, 55 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 25)
    On the audio track you can hear people talking in a different language, animal noises and other noises.; Format: 35mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - L.S. Party Into Stream Coapman Alone, 41 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 26)
    The film showed people riding elephants; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Dr. in Grass Call Out Data; Dr. Dismounts, 1949; 41 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 27)
    On the audio track you hear man saying, "respiration 15, heart 120, temperature 102 and time 45.; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Dr. in Grass Call Out Data; Dr. Dismounts, 1949; 36 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 28)
    The film showed men sitting down on elephant and it showed a man sitting down in the bushes.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - King of Elephant After Baby Shoot, Dr. Shoots Gun, 1949; 36 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 29)
    On the audio track you can hear background noise of people talking in another language and you hear a man saying if there is any sign of danger I'll let you know right away; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - King of Elephant After Baby Shoot, Dr. Shoots Gun, 1949; 59 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 30)
    The film showed men riding on a elephant and showed the elephant lowering its self to let let one of the man off; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - LT Opening w/ Coapman, 1949; 198 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 31)
    On the audio track you can hear background noise of men talking; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - LT Opening w/ Coapman, 1949; 120 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 32)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas talking with elephants and men in the background. Lowell Thomas was then talking to one of the men; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Interview with Scott, opening on elephant, 80 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 33)
    On the audio track you can hear Lowell Thomas talking about a bomb on a plane and was talking about Africa. You also hear him talking about what age is appropriate to capture Rhino; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Interview with Scott, opening on elephant, linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 34)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas standing next to a man talking with elephants behind them; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, N/A - Audio track only; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Interview with Scott, opening on elephant, 148 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 35)
    On the audio track you can hear Lowell Thomas talking about a man name John and that he is the first of missionary family to go into business. You can hear John talking about opportunities about preserving a rhino.; Format: 35mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Interview with Scott, opening on elephant, 340 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 36)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas talking to man with elephants and another man behind them. It showed Lowell Thomas an two other man riding on a elephant; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Fremantel in Morocco, 1958; 449 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 37)
    Audio only. Lowell Thomas reports "live" from the "Concourse of Sinners" in Marrakesh, Morocco. Entertainers performing on the street encourage passerby's to "not be stingy with their contributions." Lowell Thomas interviews American children who live in Morocco. One at a time, he asks them what their fathers do for a living. Lowell describes a little Moroccan girl at the square who had just reached womanhood at 13. She picks out a celebratory veil. Lowell Thomas narrates the process of men dying fabrics and leather.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 40 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 38)
    The film showed a man carving a whole in what looked like a tree trunk and after he had finished carving it out, it showed other men that was helping to put an animal skin over it. I believe they had created a drum. The film was kind of dark since it was black and white, so I couldn't see what was going on.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 140 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 39)
    A large plant blowing in the breeze. A closeup of a bush.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 1102 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 40)
    A man butchering a goat. Shears it, and hangs it upside-down. Men are dressed in robes.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 64 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 41)
    A man harvesting a crop [grain?]. Uses a donkey to plow the fields.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 53 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 42)
    The outside of a home. Someone starting a fire, others making bread and pottery. Women are walking while carrying container of water on their heads.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Morocco, 1958; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 43)
    Lowell Thomas narration of an event in Morocco [grand opening of a highway?]. The modernization of Morocco.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Africa, 1961; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 44)
    Title credits, African man, man speaking to a crowd of people, crowd of people, men having a conference, city, suit cases, person dragging the luggages, man in suit, athlete, someone dancing, native people, woman's face, man with spear, people gathering, people marching together, two men wrestling, people walking by a wall, two people in the middle of an open field, man checking inside tent, people sitting by small house, close up of a man's face, two people by a house, man jogging, animals standing by the tree, native statue, two women dressing a woman up; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Africa, 1961; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 45)
    African man, close up of native man holding spear, men grouping up with spears, people exchanging weapons, man holding two spears, men siting together, man standing alone, man in suit, men meeting with each other, man bowing, crowd of people, people walking in a big group, large crowd of people, man wearing a hat, close up of pipe instrument, people from the states, men clapping, people playing the violin, man in middle of crowd, man shaking hands with people, man in robe, man in robe shaking hands, lady wearing hat, two kids wearing hats, little girl, man and woman watching, man and woman standing together, 3 men bowing, woman standing by the crowd; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Africa, 1961; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 46)
    men standing together, man greeting other men, man stretching his arms out, people standing in line, close up of man and woman, close up of man, man tithing something, close up of man walking, outside of building area, man standing with pole, close up of native, native person dancing, two men walking toward a crowd of people, plane by the lake, air view of land, native man staring up, native woman, old man with walking stick, people drumming, people gathered around drummer, side view of native, snake, snake on tree, buildings, man in office, title screen, people's legs, 3 old men talking, woman holding baby, close up of drum, man on horse; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Africa, 1961; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 47)
    landscape, man in suit, close up of man's arm, hand pointing to map, man explaining about map, forest, plane flying, bird flying over clouds, sky view of land, mountains, native dancing, overhead view of river, frog, grasshopper, snake, lizard, monkey, deer, elephant, man fixing something, men with tiger skin, people sitting inside, two people talking, native man laughing, two men talking outside, outside view of cabin, bear, alligator, animals in lake, bushes, bird, tiger, giraffe, horde of animals, men walking into bushes, two people looking into the view; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Africa, 1961; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 48)
    people discussing, two people looking toward the lake, animal eating grass, lake, person looking towards the lake, lake water, people talking by the lake, cabin by the lake,; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Africa, 1957; linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 49)
    Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Fremantel in Morocco, 341 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 50)
    People standing outside a building. A street festival, people gathered together a man is fire breathing. People playing drums, and drinking from a pot. Shot of a small city. A store front reads "Spoutnik" which translates to "made in Morocco". Soldiers standing in formation with tanks and military vehicles. Lowell Thomas speaking. People rowing and dressed in costume. Boxes piled up on at a port labelled "Delco". Riding camels, and elephants. Dancing, a shot of a tiger. Credits read "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas". "Narrated by Lowell Thomas and Prosper Buranelli. Directed by Victor Stoloff. Odyssey Productions".; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Fremantel in Morocco, 92 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 51)
    Lowell Thomas addresses the camera as he walks through the "Concourse of Sinners," in Marrakesh, Morocco. We see street performers dance and play instruments. A man sticks pink into his eyes; onlookers applaud. Lowell Thomas interviews American children. We see people exploring the shops. A young girl picks out a veil. Men pour liquid into different holes in the ground. Fabrics are dunked into the liquid.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio:; Type: Negative
  - Tripoli- to insert after dome of Balbo palace, 1945; 935 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1015)
    Outside of British Military Court building, streets of Tripoli, and a well.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Africa, 1959; 705 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1123)
    "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas". (last reel of this episode) Directred by Victor Stoloff. In this episode, Lowell Thomas meets taxidermist Zimmerman. He then travels to Madagascar, where he witnesses its inhabitants celebrating the continuation of life in death by digging up their deceased ancestors, as well as the rituals surrounding a couple getting married. Contains concluding message by sponsor, General Motors Delco-Remy batteries, a preview for the next episode of "High Adventure with Lowell Thomas" in Tibet, and closing credits. Copyright 1958.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Black & White; Audio: Optical; Type: Positive
  - Coapman + Elephants, 773 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1124)
    Lowell Thomas and a few other men plan out a shelter of sorts that they are looking to build to hold the 3 elephant babies that have just been born. They also plan out their tactics to trap and shoot a rhino using their elephants. There are also brief recordings of the men actually trapping the rhino.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Letter arung, baby rhino, rhino in pen, carried off, 890 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1125)
    On the audio track you can hear people talking in a different language, you hear water noises and you hear a man saying that they were going through the trees and leaves. He was also saying where the people are going and how they are capturing a rhino.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Positive
  - Galina, 499 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1126)
    The film starts with a few guys pushing out a small boat and to go fishing while the sun is low on the horizon. Elephants are shown relaxing in a river before walking off with men on their backs. In another scene where the elephants are carrying more people and luggage through the grass, a man is shown standing on an elephant and shooting down a rhino which is then measured before being carried off. People gather around a small group of children who dance while a man plays a drum.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - unlabeled, 1949; 629 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1127)
    The film showed people riding on elephants hunting down rhino's in tall bushes.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive
  - Hunting party trekking out water, elephants, 1969; 616 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1128)
    Lowell Thomas and crew ride elephants on safari. The elephants follow each other in a line through tall grass. Then the elephants walk through a shallow river.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type: Positive